Saul Ortigoza

Sr. Staff Cloud Architect / Site Reliability Engineer / DevOps / Engineering Manager

Experienced technology leader with a demonstrated history of working in software development and cloud computing. Proficient in a variety of languages, tools, and practices.

Cloud (7+ years): AWS, GCP

Containers (7+ years): Kubernetes, Docker

Practices (8+ years): CI/CD, DevOps, QA, Serverless **Tools (7+ years):** Terraform, Jenkins, Ansible, Automation

Languages: Python (10+ years), Ruby (4+ years), Golang (2+ years), Java, JavaScript

Soft Skills: Critical Thinking, Leadership, Strategy

Email: sortigoza.jobs@gmail.com

Twitter: @saul_ortigoza
GitHub: @sortigoza
LinkedIn: saul-ortigoza
Resume: PDF Link

Certifications

- Amazon Web Services: Solutions Architect Professional (Certified)
- ISTQB Advanced Test Analyst Level (Certified)

Professional Experience

Cerby (2022-Present)

Senior SRE, Data Engineer, Software Engineer

- Architected and developed the application authorization (RBAC) system.
- Contributed to the design and development of numerous EPM features including Teams, Secrets,
 Collections, and Partnerships.
- Designed and developed a global message bus system for the platform.
- Created the Zero-knowledge and local-encryption architectures.

Wizeline (2020-2022)

Cloud Operations Discipline Lead / Engineering Manager

- Set the direction for the SRE discipline by establishing OKRs, SRE Communities.
- Improved the SRE discipline through coaching, mentoring, and initiating show-and-tell initiatives.
- Grew the SRE and cloud organization through hiring, training, and publishing articles (8x growth).
- Improved employee engagement.
- Managed a multi-disciplinary team of up to 24 engineers.

Wizeline (2019-2022)

Senior Staff SRE / DevOps

- Led the architecture and development of the next-gen data platform initiative for a FinTech client.
- Provided valuable guidance and input to multiple clients and projects.
- Led the team to achieve AWS DevOps-competence.

Wizeline (2017-2019)

Senior Site Reliability Engineer / DevOps Engineer

- Managed cloud environments for various company and customer projects.
- Enabled development teams to deploy releases following CI/CD practices.
- Designed, planned, and implemented cloud solution architectures for web and data services.
- Monitored and improved DevOps metrics.
- Led SRE for the internal bots platform and other projects.
- Conducted talks about DevOps practices, containerization, and CI/CD practices.
- Prepared the team and infrastructure to successfully obtain a SOC2 certification.

Continental (2016-2017)

Systems Test Manager

- Managed a team of 5+ engineers across 4 simultaneous projects.
- Implemented both traditional and Kanban methodologies for project planning, monitoring, controlling, and risk assessment.
- Participated actively and collaborated globally within the test manager community.

Continental (2014-2017)

Test Automation Engineer

- Created the architecture and implemented the testing tool-chain and framework for the test department, catering to embedded systems.
- Set up and managed Linux application servers for the QA department, including web applications, databases, GitLab, Nginx, RESTful APIs.
- Served as the go-to person for programming and automation solutions.
- Developed tooling applications for testing support using Ruby, Python, and Java (Backend and libraries).

- Worked with the Tire Pressure Monitoring System (TPMS) algorithms and functions, the PASE system, and computer vision algorithms.
- Designed and automated generic test specs for multiple functionalities and platforms.

AppCo (Startup) (2015-2017)

Lead Software Architect

- Led a team of 5 engineers.
- Architected and designed software applications using Ruby on Rails, Android, Sinatra, NodeJS.
- Conducted analysis, evaluation, and selection of development technologies.
- Developed web and mobile applications.
- Integrated with third-party services, such as Facebook, Google, Paypal, Conekta, Wordpress.
- Automated deployment and provisioning.

Interactive Cozumel (2013-2014)

Software Engineer

Education

The Institute of Technology at Linköping University (2009-2013)

Bachelor's degree, Mechatronics, Robotics, and Automation Engineering

- Completed courses in Signal Processing, Advanced Control, Machine Learning, Advanced Mathematics.
- Participated in projects involving Machine Learning, DSP, Sensor Fusion Algorithms, and Digital Filters.

Instituto Tecnológico y de Estudios Superiores de Monterrey / ITESM (2009-2013)

Bachelor's degree, Mechatronics, Robotics, and Automation Engineering

Accomplishments

As an **SRE Engineering Manager**, I've consistently provided valuable and timely feedback to all Engineers, helping them align their career growth with the Discipline and company goals. Over a span of 2+ years, this has resulted in:

- A high-performing team where everyone is either a mentor or a mentee.
- Five plus promotions approved by a committee.
- Five plus projects with long recurring renovations.
- 70% team participation in Hiring initiatives.
- More than 65% of the team certified in AWS, GCP, Terraform, k8s.
- Five SRE community champions.

For a FinTech customer, the data-platform we created significantly improved the data team's capabilities, scalability, performance, and compliance. The platform transformed from a brittle, manual, and GUI-based flow to a fully compliant CI/CD process, enabling swift changes in infrastructure, data models, and DAGs. The time spent on new database integrations reduced from 3+ days per table to integrating a whole schema in just 1 hour.

Other key initiatives for the FinTech customer included:

- Redefining the AWS permissions strategy and implementing an Okta-AWS permissions and authentication system, making the entire company's AWS authentication more efficient.
- Refactoring data-intensive and ML microservices to enable extensibility.
- Discovering and implementing a no-code/low-code solution aimed at improving the experience and efficiency of the operation teams.
- Contributing to the migration of a monolith to Kubernetes and defining a strategy to manage Kubernetes manifests with |sonnet.

Continued Learning

In the past year, I've expanded my technical knowledge in several areas:

- **Clojure:** To expose myself to different programming perspectives and practice functional programming. I've read the book "Clojure Applied."
- **Snowflake, DBT, DVC, SageMaker:** I familiarized myself with these technologies to better understand and provide recommendations to the data team.
- **GraphQL:** Acquired practical knowledge and application.
- **Software Design:** Read "Patterns of Enterprise Application Architecture" by Martin Fowler, "Software Design Decoded", and "Engineering Software Products" for a refresher.

In leadership and management, I've read and applied principles from several books:

- "Radical Candor" by Kim Scott
- "The Score Takes Care of Itself" by Bill Walsh
- "Principles" by Ray Dalio
- "Infonomics" by Douglas B. Laney

Additional Notes: Articles

- How to ensure DevOps practices in a project
- A day in the life: What does a site reliability engineer do?